Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection - Library Special Collections, ca. 1198-1616
UCLA Library Special Collections
- The Charles E. Young Research Library: Department of Special Collections.
  - MISSAL AND LIBER CENSUUM of Uckerath. Germany (Uckerath), s. XII-XVI., *170/527.; Fig. 6; Parchment, 17 loose folios of varying dates with an incorrect eighteenth-century foliation; original size ca. 380 × 265 mm., more or less deeply torn with damage to the text. 1 (frontispiece), s. XVI/XVII. 
    10) ff. 11v-15, 17: Liber censuum of the church for the year 1503, with additions (f. 12, A.D.1516); insertions not concerning the Liber censuum on f. 12v (seventeenth century), 13v (A.D.1552).
    11) ff. 15v-16v: Records of offerings to the church, six of them dated 1512; (f. 17, end of the Liber censuum for 1503) f. 17v notes dated 1539, 1556, 1605.
    Written in Germany by or for the parish church of Uckerath, Siegkreis, in the archdiocese of Cologne, where it remained and continued in use from the twelfth through the seventeenth century or later;1 concerning Uckerath see F.W. Oediger, ed., Die Erzdiözese Köln um 1300 1: Der Liber valoris, Publications of the Gesellsch. für Rhein. Geschichtskunde vol.12 (1967) p.101. Given to UCLA ca. 1936 by Edmund M. Riese. A palimpsest and a bifolium from Uckerath cataloged below among the loose leaves, 1/XII/Ger/4 and 2/XII/Ger/5, which were given to UCLA by Mr. Riese at the same time, probably once belonged to the missal; but the identification is not positive.
    1. We are grateful to V. Honemann and the Institut für historische Landesforschung der Universität Güttingen for the identification of Uckerath.
  - COMMONPLACE BOOK OF LAURENCE NOWELL. England, ca. 1560-ca. 1571., 170/529.; Figs. 28-30; Paper (Chapeau and Lettre B, not found in Briquet), ff. 276 (includes unnumbered leaf after f. 59, and f. 242bis); 155 × 105 mm. Varying numbers of lines; unruled, except for occasional bounding lines in lead point. Written in several tiny Elizabethan scripts mainly by Laurence Nowell,1 except for items in the hand of William Lambarde: ff. 135v, 199v, 187v-192v, 205v-207, 210.; Bound in contemporary limp parchment, title along the spine erased; parchment strips from a twelfth-century manuscript used as reinforcement for the spine.
    1) ff. 1-8, 9-10 blank, save for possession notes and added miscellaneous notes, ff. 8v, 10v-16v: Notes on philosophy in Greek and Latin in quasi-dictionary form.
    2) ff. 17-41: Philosophical florilegium in Greek and Latin organized by Latin headings in intermittently alphabetical order from Aberra to Veritas; f. 41v, the Greek equivalents of 3 Latin words.
    3) ff. 42-47v: Sentences and notes on geographical names in Latin, Greek, and Italian, ff. 48-52 blank.
    4) ff. 52v-53v: Geographical names with explanations in Greek, ff. 54-55v blank.
    5) ff. 56-58: Excerpts from Pausanias, in Greek.
    6) ff. 58v-59: Notes in Latin and English with dates 1553, 1554, 1560 (but written at one time), ff. 59v-59bis blank.
    7) ff. 60-72: Notes in Latin, Greek, and English on chronology, astrology, history, etc., with dates 1560 (f. 160v) and 1518 (f. 62); includes on f. 63v Bibliothecae celebres: Romae Vaticana seu pontificia, Florentiae Medicum, Bononiae S. Salvatoris, Venetiis Bessarionis, S. Ioannis et Pauli et aliae, Diegi Hurtadi. ff. 72v-79v blank.
    8) ff. 80-116: Latin-Greek dictionary from A to Ingratus, f. 116v blank.
    9) ff. 117-120: Notes on geometry in Italian (f. 119r-v blank), ff. 120v-122v blank.
    10) ff. 123r-v: List of kings of England to Henry III. ff. 124-135 blank.
    11) f. 135v: Index to ff. 136-212, which bear separate foliation 1-6 and 1-72 (the number 59 omitted).
    12) ff. 136-184v: A transcription of the Quadripartitus from Holkham Hall MS 228 (ff.141v-142, 146v-147, 179v-180 blank), ff. 185-187 blank.
    13) ff. 187v-192v: [Laws of William the Conqueror in Anglo-Norman copied from the Croyland Chronicle of “Ingulph”] Inveni in quodam Croilandiae chronico Ingulphum abbatem eiusdem detulisse secum a Londino domum usque has leges sequentes... quae ut ipse testatur hoc ipso idiomate scriptae fuerunt. (f. 188) Ces sunt les leis e les custumes... les vilains en ferme plege. [Added:] Sequuntur vide infra fol. 65 [= f. 205v].
    This part of the chronicle has not been edited in the original. Cf. Ingulph's Chronicle of the Abbey of Croyland, translated by Henry T. Riley (London, 1854) pp.175-184, sections 1-29, followed by a misplaced section 22.
    14) ff. 193-199: [Laws of William the Conqueror in Latin] Haec quae sequuntur in Gulielmi legibus ascribuntur quae in maiori libro omittuntur... ferrum triplicis Deiiudicii ponderet 3 libras. [Added:] Interponenda sunt fol. precedens: Quod sinecessitas... nisi rex ei patriam indulserit.
    15) f. 199v: Charta H. 3... toforenseid; and pet [with catchword] aelc. ff. 200-205 blank.
    The first half of Henry III's proclamation of 1258 in Middle English issued for Oxfordshire; ed. W.W. Skeat, “The Oxford Manuscript of the Only English Proclamation of Henry III,” Transactions of the Philological Society 1880-1881 app. 6pp. 169*-177*, to the middle of line 6 (Skeat p.173*).
    16) ff. 205v-207: Addenda legibus Gulihelmi gallice conscriptis post capitulum de streward. Si il que custinent la terr ne deit lome ... sil ne poit envers le voy lamende e il soil utlage. ff. 207v-209v blank.
    The completion of the laws extracted from the Croyland chronicle (cf. item 13 above); cf. Riley, sections 30-53, pp.184-188.
    17) f. 210: Ex legibus [Alfredi, corr. to:] Edgari regis quibus titulus est Her gebirađ nu to Eadgares gerædnesse be gehadodra liffadunge. We lærađ pæt godes peowas beon heora woruld lafordurn eac hold 7 getrywe. And we lærađ pæt preost ne beo hunta ne hafecere ne tæflere ac plegge on his bocum swa his hade gebryađ. Liber est Matthaei Cantuar. Archiep. 1571. W[illelmus] L[ambardus].
    Two excerpts from the so-called Canons of Edgar: Roger Fowler, ed., Wulfstan's Canons of Edgar, EETS no.266 (London, 1972) pp.2 and 14. Copied from Cambridge, Corpus Christi College Manuscript 201 which belonged to Matthew Parker, archbishop of Canterbury.
    18) f. 211: Ex libro 3° Willelmi Malmesbyrie de regibus, ubi has quae sequuntur legibus Willelmi regis magni ascribit. Regem Angliae singulari maiestate... molimine semper infrendit. ff. 211v-274v blank.
    William of Malmesbury, Gesta regum anglorum book 3; ed. Thomas D. Hardy, vol.2 (London 1840, reproduced 1964) 473n-474n.
    1. We are grateful to Carl T. Berkout for identifying a number of the contents of this manuscript and especially for distinguishing the hands of Nowell and Lambarde
    Written in England between ca. 1560 and ca. 1567 by Laurence Nowell (d. ca. 1570); his signature, f. 2; concerning Nowell's dates and identity see now Carl T. Berkout, “The Pedigree of Laurence Nowell the Antiquary,” English Language Notes vol.23, no.2 (1985) pp.15-26. Belonged to Nowell's friend William Lambarde (1536-1601) who wrote additional material between ca. 1567 and ca. 1571; his signature also on f. 2. On ff. 2, 118, 210, 274, forgeries of various Shakespeare signatures: f.2, “William Shakspere 1590” (almost obliterated with pen strokes); f. 118, “William Shaksp(e)r(e), Oxforde” (copy of the second signature in Shakespeare's will of 1616); f. 210, “William Shaksp(ere) 1590” (copy of the third signature in the will of 1616); f. 274, initials “W.S.”; for facsimiles of forged autographs of Shakespeare see S.A. Tannenbaum, Problems in Shakespeare's Penmanship, Including a Study of the Poet's Will (New York, 1927) plates 39-42; the present forgeries possibly date from the twentieth century. Sold by Hodgson (19 June 1924, lot 512) to Myers & Company, London. Belonged to C.K. Ogden (1889-1957); his bookplate, inside the front cover. Acquired by UCLA with the Ogden library in 1958.
    A copy of this book is UCLA Negative Microfilm no.05428.
  - ORSINI COLLECTION. Italy, s. XIV-s. XX., COLLECTION 902.
    The archive of the Orsini family, in 532 boxes, includes roughly 1000 items that date before the year 1600. A one-volume typescript inventory of the collection was compiled by Evert Volkersz in 1967.
    Acquired by UCLA in 1967.
    G. Billanovich, Tra don Teofilo Folengo e Merlin Cocaio (Naples, 1948) p.174.
    A copy of the inventory is UCLA Negative Microfilm no.06423.
  - GIUGNI FAMILY ACCOUNT BOOK. Italy (Tuscany, Garbo?), 1580-1586., COLLECTION 952, BOX 1.; Paper, ff. 192 (contemporary foliation 1 to 8 and 41 to 68 in a double series, in roman numerals on the upper right of the recto and in arabic numerals on the upper left of the verso); 330 × 230 mm. 1-1216. Written by Raffaello Giugni in an Italian cursive.; Contemporary envelope binding in parchment over limp cardboard reinforced with three leather straps, one of which encircles and fastens the volume with a flap; on the front cover in a contemporary hand, “Entrata e uscita”; under the flap, a large (45 mm. × 45 mm.) “A”; on the spine, “1581-1586.”
    ff. 1-68: [Accounts of the Giugni family, from 22 December 1580 to 16 September 1586] Yhesus Maria. Al nome sia dello onnipotente et immortale Idio padre figliuolo et spirito sancto e della gloriosissima madre Maria sempre vergine dello unigienito figliuolo di Dio vocato Jesu creatore di questo secolo e redentore della humana generatione e delli altri santi e sante desso Idio equali tutti suplichiamo che si degnino interciedere per noi che insuquesto libro si scriva cose utile per lanima e per il corpo a laude e gloria de Dio e de sua santi. Ammen. Questo libro e di Raffaello, Antonio, Niccolo fratelli e figli di Andrea di Raffaello di Rinieri Giugni heredi di detto Andrea per la heredita di Andrea detto e altre loro facciende principiato dappoi la morte di detto Andrea, intitolato Entrata e uscita, signato A. Da carte l sino a carte quaranta sara entrata, da carte quaranta sino fine sara uscita. ff. 1v-8 [credit accounts] Yhesus, MDLXXXI. Entrata di danari contanti che si risquoteranno per Raffaello, Antonio, Niccolo Gtugni fratelli e figli di Andrea Giugni tenuta per mano di me Raffaello Giugni, cominciata addi 22 dicembre 1581 [1580 N.S.].. .; ff. 8v-40v blank; ff. 41-68 [debit accounts] Yhesus. MDLXXXI. Uscita di danari contanti che si pagheranno per Raffaello, Antonio, Niccolo Giugni fratelli e figli di Andrea di Raffaello Giugni tenuta per mano di me Raffaello Giugni cominciata addi 22 dicembre, e prima.... ff. 68v-192v blank.
    Written in Tuscany, presumably in Garbo, by Raffaello Giugni. There are two later account books in this box: Raffaello Giugni's accounts for his business in Garbo, 1613-1626; and the credits and debits of Lucretia, widow of Cosimo Gorini, in Tuscany, 1642-1657. A part of the Corsini Collection, which came to UCLA after World War II; the source and date of acquisition are unknown.
  - COLLECTION 952, BOX 2., (2 items)
    - CONVENT OF S. MARIA DEGLI ANGELI, ACCOUNT BOOK. Italy (Tuscany, Lucca?), 1540-1546., Paper, ff. i (parchment) + 192 (numbered 1-191 with first leaf unnumbered) + i; 280 × 202 mm. 1-1216. Written by several Italian cursive hands, including Sr. Caterina, ff. 78-98v and entries on 99-103v, I04-108v, 139-140v.; Contemporary envelope binding in limp parchment reinforced by three leather straps, one fastening the volume with a buckle; on the front cover: “G” and “Giornale.”; Flyleaves: Fragments of Gregory I, Moralia, written in central Italy, s. XI2 Text begins on back flyleaf verso “//suam appetit quia... ,” ends on front flyleaf recto ”... et remissionem peccatorum per omnes gentes//”; Moralia 28.7-29.14, PL 76.485D-491B. Two parchment leaves originally conjugate, 4 and 5 of a quire of 8; cropped top and bottom, original written space ca. 290 × 185 mm.; in 2 cols., originally of 40 lines; ruled in drypoint, double bounding lines. Written in brown ink in a late developed Caroline minuscule script, showing the peculiar ri-ligature; et appears as both ampersand and tironian 7; both uncial and upright d; small s-shape abbreviation marks for b(us) and q(ue). Brown majuscule initials, touched with yellow. Marginalia by the hand of the text; carefully revised by a contemporary corrector. Written in central Italy, and used for binding in a region not far from its place of origin some five centuries later.
      ff. iv-140v: Accounts of the Dominican nuns of S. Maria degli Angeli from 1540 to 1546. ff. iv-98v Debit accounts from December 1540 (N.S.) to February 1544; ff. 99-103v Miscellaneous records in several hands, including occasional accounts from February 1544 to November 1545 (N.S.); ff. 104-108v: [credit accounts, 1545-1546] A entrata del nostro monasterio di Sancta Maria degli Angeli la quale entrata scrivera Suora Caterina al presente priora del capitolo e convento di Santa Maria degli Angdi del terzo ordine di San Domenico delta Penitentia. Al nome di Dio. Sabato adi 13 di novembre 1546 ( = 1545 N.S.); ff. 109-138v blank; ff. 139-140v Debit accounts, December 1545 (N.S.)-Jan. 1546. ff. 141-191v blank.
      A part of the Corsini collection; See COLLECTION 952, BOX 1. Source and date of acquisition by UCLA are unknown.
    - CAMBINI FAMILY ACCOUNT BOOK. Italy (Florence), 1531-1647., Paper, ff. i + 158; 290 × 220 mm. 116 (2-3 16missing; ff. 16-47v) 4-1216. Written in Italian cursive script by different hands including that of Lorenzo Cambini (ff. 87-183).; Contemporary envelope binding in limp parchment with three leather straps, one fastening the volume with a buckle; on the front cover: “Entrata e uscita,” “A”;on the spine: “1531-1540.”
      1) ff. i-86: Cambini family accounts, ff. iv -8 Credit accounts, from December 1531 (N.S.) to June 1540 (N.S.); f. 8v blank; f. 9 Addition with the date 1569; f. 9v blank; f. 10r-v Notes of harvests for 1635-1644; ff. 11-15v blank; ff. 16-47v missing; f. 48 Notes for the years 1639-1644; ff. 48v-55v blank; ff. 56-84v Debit accounts, from December 1531 (N.S.) to June 1540 (N.S.); ff. 8-86 Additions for the years 1543-1547; f. 86v Addition for 1544 crossed out.
      On the Cambini family of Florence see Dizionario biografico degli italiani 17 (1974) 132-136; and R. de Roover, The Rise and Decline of the Medici Bank (1397-1494) (Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1963) pp.91, 255.
      2) ff. 87-150v: [Accounts of the Cambini estate of La Sassaia, 1638-1645] Da qui in avanti servirà per diverse rnemorie tenute da Lorenzo Cambini per interesse del podere della Sassata come appresso(ff. 87v, 89-103v, 106-129v, 133v-139v, 141v-144v, 145v-150, 151-179v blank); ff. 180-183 Notes recording the harvesting of trees on the estate, 1610-1656. ff. 183v-190v blank.
  - CARLO DI ANDREA CAMBINI, ACCOUNT BOOK. Italy (Florence), 1556-1616., COLLECTION 952, BOX 3.; Paper, ff. 192 (contemporary foliation I-CLXXXXVIII with gaps); 280 × 215 mm. 1-824. Written in Italian cursive script by one main hand (ff. 1-99v), with later additions.; Contemporary envelope binding with three leather straps, one fastening the volume with a buckle; on the front cover: “Debitori e creditori,” “Cambini,” “A”; on the spine: “1556-1605.”
    ff. 1-198v [Accounts from 1556 to 1594, with additions] Yhesus. In nome di Dio et della madre Maria. Amen. Questo libro e di Carlo d'Andrea di Bartolomeo Chambini citadino fiorentino, chiamasi Debitori e creditori. Carta 1a di 198 servira per tenere gli chonti di dare ed avere. If. 1v-99v Credits and debits from 1556 to 1594; ff. 99v-102 Occasional accounts from 1600 to 1616; ff. 102v-198 blank; f. 198v Notes of payment with dates 1566-1567.
    Written in Italy, presumably Florence. In this same box are two later account books of Lorenzo di Andrea di Carlo Cambini of Florence, dated 1623-1655 and 1653-1660. A part of the Corsini collection; See Collection 952, Box 1. Source and date of acquisition by UCLA are unknown.
  - BIAGIO CASTELLANI, NOTARIAL REGISTER. Italy (Pistoia), 1382-1391., COLLECTION 952, BOX 4.; Paper, ff. 100; 290 × 220 (215/240 × 120/145) mm. 1-218 3-616 31-34 long lines, unruled. Written by Biagio Castellani in Italian littera cancelleresca. ff. 1-24 damaged by a large hole in the lower half of the page, with loss of text; ff. 1-5 also lack upper right corner with further loss of text.; Loose gatherings wrapped in a limp cover; title, s. XVIII: “Documenti di Casa Salvagnoli.”
    ff. 1-100: [Register of the deeds drawn up by Biagio Castellani of Larciano, resident of Montevettolino in Val di Nievole, Pistoia, 4 December 1382 (N.S.)-31 May 1391 (N.S.)] In nomine domini. Amen. Hie est <...> continens in se omnia instrumenta <...> scripta et edita et rogata per <...> Castellani notarium de Larciano <...> -li in districtu Florentino et scripta <...> notarium antedictum partim sub anno <...> trecentesimo octogesimo tertio indictione <...> infrascriptis nec non partim sub anno M<...> quarto indictione partim septima et partim indictione oc<tava.. .> mensibus(?) infrascriptis. Signum mey [his sign] Blaxii notarii antedicti... Et ego Blaxius filius quondam Castellani comitatus Pistorii nec non terrigena Castri Montivectulini provincie Vallis Nebule destrictus Florentini, imperiali auctoritate Iudex ordinarius atque notarius publicus, predictis omnibus et singulis suprascriptis in presenti libro dum agerentur interfui et ea rogatus scribere scripsi et fideliter publicavi ideoque me subscripsi et signum meum apposui consuetum.
    Written by Biagio Castellani presumably in Pistoia. In this same box are four medical manuscripts from later centuries: (i) De febribus, s. XVIIex, ff. 71; (ii)Seminario medico prattico s. XVIII, pp. 300; (iii) Libro di secreti medicinali pratticati dal dottor Joachim Lampranti filosofo e medico ebreo raccolti da varii libri d'eruditissimi signori e prencipi grandi et esperimentati più volte nel corso di tanti anni di sua prattica esercitata in Padova ed in attri luoghi e specialmente in Ferrara, s, XVIII, 4 fascicles + ff. 220 + 4 fascicles; (iv) Farmacopea di Torino tradotta dal latino in italiano idioma da me Giovanni Beriollo, s. XVIIIex, pp. 234. A part of the Corsini collection; See COLLECTION 952, BOX 1. Source and date of acquisition by UCLA are unknown.
  - SIENESE FISCAL RECORDS. Italy (Siena), 1601-1615., COLLECTION 952, BOX 5.; Parchment, ff. xviii (paper) + 240; 213 × 145 mm.; Bound in contemporary blind-stamped half leather over wooden boards. Two medieval pastedowns:; (i) [Justinian, Codex; Italy, s. XIII] //Imp. Negotiandi causa edificia... future non timeat detrimentum// [C., 8, 10, 2-9]. Upper portion of 1 leaf, 150 × 213 mm. 2 cols., of which 22 lines survive; gloss surrounding the text, of which 37 incomplete lines survive; ruling not discernible. Written in Italian gothic bookhand in university style (littera bononiensis); initials alternately red and blue. Another strip from this same manuscript, 65 × 210 mm., is pasted in the spine.; (ii) [Office of the dead; Italy, s. XV) //tue de corpore... Libera domine animam servi// 1 leaf, 220 × 160 (155 × 105) mm. 2 cols., of 31 lines; ruling not discernible. Written in an Italian gothic bookhand in liturgical style (littera textualis formata); initials and rubrics in red.
    Libro autentico di compere, di effetti e censi di Piano e Potentino nello Stato Senese dal 1601 al 1615.
    Another late manuscript is kept in this same box: Bartolomeo Dotti, Poesie e satire, s. XVIII, pp. 1170. A part of the Corsini collection; See COLLECTION 952, BOX 1. Source and date of acquisition by UCLA are unknown.
  - NEAPOLITAN MISCELLANY. Italy (Naples?), s. XVI., COLLECTION 953, BOX 1 NO.3.; Paper, ff, i + 55; 271 × 205 mm. Written by several late humanistic hands.; Bound in limp vellum, s. XVIII, with a large miscellany of later printed and manuscript items.
    [ff. 49-55 are bound before ff. 1-48].
    1) ff. 1-16v: Sanfelice della Campagna felice a Elio Marches di famiglie [Antonio Sanfelice, Campania (Naples, 1562 etc.)]; the heading is on f. iv. f. 17r-v blank.
    2) ff. 18-49v: [Francesco Elto Marchesi] IX novembris MDLIX. Francisci Aelii Marchesii Neapolitani De nobilium familiarum origine libellus ad Hieronymum Carbonem Neapolitanum... VIII Dec. describere explevi horis succisivis ob negociorum molem, sed desiderium atque aviditas mira hęc audiendi et memorię mandandi omnia superavit. Antonius Feltrius bona fide ex codice qui LX propemodum annis latuerat.
    Other manuscript copies of this work are recorded in Kristeller, Iter italicum, vol.1, no.127, 353, 397; vol.2, no.96, 332, 341, 450, 451, 470.
    3) ff. 53-52: [38 couplets] Augustino Nipho medici philosopho Hieronymus Carbo. Liber ago in terris vitam sine turbine rerum... O decus et verę nobilitatis Amor: Finis.
    Concerning Girolamo Carbone see Dizionario biografico degli italiani vol.19 (1976) pp.695-698.
    4) f. 52v: <... tear... >-ns Alexandrinus In oratione adhortatoria ad Gręcos sive ad Gentes, f.23. Solent enim nescio quomodo... etiam haberi in admiratione.
    5) f. 53r-v: Ioannis Casae ad Galeatium Florimontis Ut Capta reditus Helena cum coniugio Troia... Nixa diu tandem plagis perterrita currit.
    60 verses, not included in Opere di Monsignor Giovanni della Casa, ed. A. Pasinelli, 5 vols. (Venice, 1728-1729).
    6) f. 54r-v: Prestantissimo iuveni Colae Antonio Caracciolo Marchioni Vici Paulus Manutius S.P.D. [E. Pastorello, L 'epistolario manuziano: Inventario cronologico-analitico 1483-1597 (Venice, 1957) no. 1052: Rome, 28 February 1562]. f. 55 Notes in various hands, including the name “Hannibal Caraciolo” and the date 1561.
    7) f. 55v: [Antonio Sanfelice, three Latin couplets] F. Antonii Santofelicin. Moribus antiques senioque... est inimica probis.
    Two other volumes are kept in this box: (i) a miscellany of sixteenth- and seventeenth-century manuscript copies of earlier documents (A.D. 1182 to s. XVI) relevant to the Kingdom of Naples, bound with miscellaneous printed items, and (ii) Gaspare Deodato Zamponi, Del Regno di Napoli, Memorie, indrizzate agli eccellentissimi Signori della Reggenza, s. XVIII; and there are three other boxes of late miscellaneous materials, printed and manuscript, concerning the history of Naples (Collection 953, Boxes 2-4). Each volume, including the present, bears two armorial bookplates with mottoes “Ex libris Marchionis Salsae” and “Comme je fus,” found also in Manuscript 170/292. Among the materials bound in the present volume are verses in several hands, with dates in the 1770s, dedicated to the “Eccellentissima Signora Donna Gioseffa Malaspina, Marchesa di Salsa.” Acquired by UCLA in 1966 from an unknown source.
  - PIERRE GAUTIER, MISCELLANEA. France (Paris and Orleéans), 1572-1575., COLLECTION 968, BOX 1, NO.71.; Fig. 33; Paper, ff. iii + 188; 210 × 160 (170/190 × 110/125) mm. Quires of 8 leaves. Long lines and (ff. 177-187) 2 cols., 32/41 lines per page. Written by one hand, the legal and literary matter in italic script (ff. 1-94v, 109v-112v, 142-187), the scientific matter in chancery script (ff. 101-109, 113-141v).; Contemporary binding in limp parchment; remains of a paper label on the spine.
    1) ff. 1-75v: Miscellanea id est variae de variis rebus sententiae a me collectae... Hic substiti 4 Idus lulii 1574, cum de discessu cogitare inciperem et quatuor pauloplus annis Lutetiae mora facta, patrios lares repetere proponerem. Laus Deo.
    2) ff. 76-81: Poemata latina P. Galteri [with the date 1574 on f. 81].
    3) ff. 81v-82v: Legal notes.
    4) ff. 93-98: Poesie francoise [with the dates 1573 (f. 84), 1574 (f. 87), and, bottom of f.87:] 1575 Aureliae, mense Iulio.
    5) ff. 87v-94v: Aureliae haec conscripsi [in margin], Continuantur miscellanea que superius ad fol. 76 usque perducta sunt [legal notes].
    6) ff. 95-100 [printed fascicle:] Institutio physica perbrevis et dilucida (Paris: Officina Thomae Brumennii, 1572) [with extensive manuscript glosses], f. 100v blank.